Guide to the Osborne Family Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Osborne family papers
1871-1950
SC0636
Osborne family.
3.25 Linear feet (6 boxes)
Correspondence, photographs, books, and other papers of Henry A. and Helen Annas Osborne and their five children, all of whom attended Stanford University.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchased 1972 and 2002.
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography
Henry Z. Osborne (1848-1923) was owner/editor of the Los Angeles Evening Express (1884-1897), gold miner, and California state representative from 1917 until his death in 1923. He was married to Helen Annas (formerly of Cazenovia, New York). All five of their children attended Stanford University. Sherrill B. Osborne, A.B. in law 1897, was managing editor of the Daily Palo Alto during his sophomore year and editor in chief during his junior year. Henry Z. Osborne, Jr., A.B. in civil engineering 1897, was active in the Civil Engineers' Club and Class Historian during his senior year. Both Sherrill and Henry also wrote for San Francisco newspapers while at Stanford. Raymond G. Osborne and Edith Osborne Stahl attended from 1903-1906. Clarence B. Osborne earned his A.B. in geology in 1909.
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers primarily consist of letters between the parents and their children during their student years at Stanford (1893-1909) and letters from the younger children to the older ones at Stanford, with some additional correspondence from family and friends (1871-1911). Other items include a biographical sketch of Henry Z. Osborne, Raymond Osborne's notebook on surveying, 1906, photographs, and books. Sherrill and Henry's letters, 1894-1897, comment on the health and schoolwork of their younger siblings, their father's newspaper, their study habits, life in Encina Hall, the 1894 frosh-soph tie-up, football and other athletic events, trips to San Francisco, and their work writing for San Francisco newspapers. Clarence, Edith, and Raymond's letters comment on their schoolwork and study habits, social life, football games, trips to San Francisco, and visits with Mrs. Dunn on campus.
Arrangement note
The materials are arranged in three series: 1) Correspondence; 2) Books; and 3) Photographs.
Access Terms
Osborne, Clarence B.; Osborne, Henry Zenas,, 1848-1923.; Osborne, Raymond G.; Osborne, Sherrill B.; Stahl, Edith Osborne; Stanford University. Department of Athletics.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1871-1912; Series 1
  - Family Letters, 1871-1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from family and friends, 1890-1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters by Henry Jr., 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters by Sherrill, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters by Mr. and Mrs. Osborne, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Osborne's from family and friends, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters by Clarence, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters by Edith, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters by Henry Jr. (includes poem he wrote for his younger siblings), 1894 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters by Henry Jr., 1894 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters by Raymond, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters by Sherrill, 1894 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters by Sherrill, 1894 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters by Mr. and Mrs. Osborne, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters by Clarence, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters by Edith, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters by Henry Jr., 1895 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters by Henry Jr., 1895 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters by Raymond, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters by Sherrill, 1895 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters by Sherrill, 1895 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters by Mr. and Mrs. Osborne, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters to Osborne's from family and friends, 1895-96 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters by Clarence, 1896-97 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters by Edith, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters by Henry Jr., 1896-97 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters by Sherrill, 1896-97 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters by Raymond, 1896-97 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters by Mr. and Mrs. Osborne, 1896-97 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters from Mrs. Osborne's mother (Grandmother Annas), 1897-1901 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters to Osborne's from family and friends, 1897-1902 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter by Mr. Osborne, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters by Clarence, 1901-03 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letters by Edith, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letters by Raymond, 1903-04 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letters from Mrs. Osborne's mother (Grandmother Annas), 1903-04 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters to Osborne's from family and friends, 1903-04 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letters from Clarence, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Edith, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letter from Sherrill, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Raymond from friends, 1904-05 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Raymond, 1905-06 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Mrs. Osborne, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Edith from Chas. T. Paine, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters by Clarence, 1907-12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Business letter to Mr. Osborne, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letter to Clarence from a friend, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reference letter for Raymond, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Biographical sketch of Henry Z. Osborne (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings re Stanford sports (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellany (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Osborne, Raymond. Notebook on surveying, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sketch of Stanford student, unsigned (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Books, 1896-1950; Series 2
  - Branner and Newsom, Syllabus of a Course of Lectures on Economic Geology (Stanford University 1900); with extensive notes (by Clarence?) (Box 3)
  - The Remick Favorite Collection of College Songs (1909) (Box 3)
  - J.C.L. Fish, Lettering of Working Drawings (1894) - inscribed "H. Z. Osborne Jr. Stanford Univ. 1895" (Box 3)
  - Holy Bible, stamped "Raymond Osborne" on cover (Box 3)
  - The Merck Manual, Eighth Edition (1950) (Box 3)
  - Report of the Director of the Mint upon the Production of the Precious Metals in the United States during the Calendar Year 1898 (1899) (Box 3)
  - Leith, C.K., Structural Geology (1913) - property of Clarence B. Osborne (Box 3)
  - Kehl, George L., The Principles of Metallographic Laboratory Practice (1943) (Box 3)
  - Crosby, W. O., Tables for the Determination of Common Minerals (1896) - property of H.Z. Osborne, Jr. (Box 3)
- Photographs, 1887-1923; Series 3
  - Stanford Images, 1895-1906
    - Charles P. Cutter in [Encina] room, Nov 20, 1895
    - Two photos of the Frosh-Soph Tie-Up, undated
    - Three images of 1906 earthquake damage: chemistry building, memorial arch, and Agassiz statue
  - Family Images, 1887-1923
    - Photograph of Clarence Osborne and son Henry, 1921
    - Portrait of Erwin Garfield Osborne, born June 8, 1880, Jan31, 1887
    - Portrait of Raymond G. Osborne, 1886
    - Two photographs of unidentified groups of people, circa 1920
    - Photograph of a damaged building ("Lincoln"), possibly from 1906 quake
    - Photograph of man in front of house (same house as below)
    - Four photographs of people on a beach, circa 1923
    - Photograph of a house, unidentified
    - Portrait of Raymond G. Osborne, 1906
    - Group portrait, possibly high school (one woman holding W '02 banner)
    - Group portrait of engineers, with Chief Deputy Henry Z. Osborne, Jr. identified [location unknown]
    - Family portrait, circa 1900
  - Earthquake images taken by Raymond Osborne, 1906
    - Chemistry and Museum: exterior of chemistry, fallen sculpture in museum lobby, 1906
    - Encina Hall: two exteriors, one interior, 1906
    - Gymnasium: four views of the front, two views of the rear of building, 1906
    - Library: two images, 1906
    - Memorial Church and quad: facade of church, ruins of arcade behind church, 1906
    - Miscellaneous: man with shotgun guarding ruins, unidentified close-up of ruined interior, 1906
- Additional Materials, Accession ARCH.2012-039
  - Letters from Osborne children to family, written while at Stanford University.
    - Letters from Clarence, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Clarence, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Clarence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Clare, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Clare, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Edith, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Edith, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Edith, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Ray, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters from Ray, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Ray, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters from Ray, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters from Sherrill, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Sherrill, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters from Sherrill, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters from Sherrill, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters from Sherrill, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1894 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Incoming letters to Osborne children, received while at Stanford University.
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1895 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Incoming letters to Henry Z., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Incoming letters to Sherrill B. and Henry Z., 1895-1897 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stanford versus Cal Debate, 1887 Apr 24 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Stanford Commencement program, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 11)